<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://amodellis.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://amodellis.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-12-06T16:29:01+00:00</updated><id>https://amodellis.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Few Notes from the Saudi Training</title><link href="https://amodellis.github.io/blog/2025/sauditraining/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Few Notes from the Saudi Training"/><published>2025-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amodellis.github.io/blog/2025/sauditraining</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amodellis.github.io/blog/2025/sauditraining/"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, as I continue establishing the Amodellis practice, I had the opportunity to deliver a four-day executive training programme for a 20-person delegation from the Ministry of Interior of Saudi Arabia. The opportunity came through an introduction from Fred Ewing and was commissioned by <em>Community Revival</em>.</p> <p>The course was titled <em>Travel Demand Modelling</em>, and I was given a rough outline to work from. The structure was sensibly progressive:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Day 1:</strong> data ecosystems and governance</li> <li><strong>Day 2:</strong> descriptive analytics and visualisation</li> <li><strong>Day 3:</strong> travel demand modelling theory</li> <li><strong>Day 4:</strong> predictive analytics</li> </ul> <p>A nice balance of fundamentals and application — enough theory to be meaningful, but not so much that the purpose of modelling got lost.</p> <hr/> <p>Below are a few reflections from my teaching experience.</p> <h4 id="visualisation-is-king"><strong>Visualisation is king</strong></h4> <p>We all <em>know</em> this, but the session made it obvious. Participants were most engaged when exploring data visually.</p> <p>Of the many official data portals demonstrated, the one that grabbed everyone’s attention was National Highways’ <a href="https://webtris.highwaysengland.co.uk"><strong>WebTRIS</strong></a>, with its clean UI and API support. Perhaps unsurprisingly, the idea of <a href="https://labs.podaris.com/unofficial-dft-connectivity-metric/"><strong>accessibility mapping</strong></a> — something I personally value a lot — felt less familiar to the group. I hope a seed of <em>transport equity</em> thinking was planted along the way.</p> <p>When it came to modelling outputs, they absolutely loved the 3D animations shown on the <a href="https://www.bentley.com/software/openpaths/#video"><strong>OpenPaths</strong></a> website.</p> <h4 id="inspiring-public-dashboards"><strong>Inspiring public dashboards</strong></h4> <p>While searching for dashboard examples, I discovered several impressive <em>unofficial</em> public transport dashboards, such as:</p> <ul> <li>the Railway Ticket Sales &amp; Ridership Dashboard by <a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/carlos.pacheco/viz/RailwayDashboard/Dashboard1"><strong>Carlos Pacheco</strong></a></li> <li>various analytics dashboards by <a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/richard.rowson/vizzes"><strong>Richard Rowson</strong></a></li> </ul> <p>There is something refreshing about well-crafted grassroots tools. Perhaps a future side-project for Amodellis.</p> <h4 id="smart-motorways-an-unexpected-crowd-favourite"><strong>Smart Motorways: an unexpected crowd favourite</strong></h4> <p>Despite their resilience with modelling theory, participants were distinctly more excited about learning how the UK’s Smart Motorway system works. I added a few slides — and happily learned a lot myself.</p> <p>Some fun facts that stood out:</p> <ol> <li>Reconfiguring parts of the motorway network into all-lane-running (ALR) smart motorways since 2023 cost <a href="https://questions-statements.parliament.uk/written-questions/detail/2025-01-07/HL3835/"><strong>£5b</strong></a> — a huge number, but still only a fraction of rail investment.</li> <li>To manage congestion and prevent shockwave braking, each motorway section is individually calibrated using historical data so that signals activate only when truly necessary.</li> </ol> <p>I also watched a TRL video on the <a href="https://smcalo.org/Home.aspx"><strong>SMCALO</strong></a> system for monitoring traffic. I now want a copy running on my own machine.</p> <h4 id="how-much-has-riyadh-changed"><strong>How much has Riyadh changed?</strong></h4> <p>I told participants about my stint in Riyadh back in 2014, when I worked on planning for the Riyadh Metro. I used to drive from the Diplomatic Quarter to Al Sulaimaniyah — driving like a maniac just to survive the flow.</p> <p>Participants assured me that things are far calmer now and invited me to return. I am not entirely convinced… especially as my own driving style has slowed with age!</p> <h4 id="the-wonderful-nano-banana-pro"><strong>The wonderful Nano Banana Pro</strong></h4> <p>My course prep coincided with the arrival of a fantastic new LLM tool for generating graphics. Text placement is no longer chaotic, and the images make coherent sense for teaching.</p> <p>It feels like a genuine step forward. At the moment, <strong>Gemini 3</strong> edges out <strong>ChatGPT-5</strong> for illustration work, at least in my hands.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2025-12-05_SaudiGraphic-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2025-12-05_SaudiGraphic-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2025-12-05_SaudiGraphic-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-12-05_SaudiGraphic.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h4 id="agentic-ai-steals-the-show"><strong>Agentic AI steals the show</strong></h4> <p>The standout moment came courtesy of <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nathan-watt-390b6165/"><strong>Nathan Watts</strong></a> from <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/transhumanity_innovation-transportmodelling-agenticai-activity-7402716914281775104-dge2"><strong>TransHumanity.AI</strong></a>, who demonstrated an agentic-AI tool capable of extracting insights from prompts about Manchester data — traffic, accidents, weather and more.</p> <p>Surprise Surpise! Participants asked more questions in his half-hour session than in the rest of the four days combined…</p> <p>The message landed clearly: <a href="/projects/service_research/"><strong>AI in transport</strong></a> is no longer optional — it is here, useful and inevitable. And hopefully Amodellis can contribute in our own small way in the future too.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="thanks-to-the-people-who-made-it-work"><strong>Thanks to the people who made it work</strong></h3> <p>This course would not have been successful without:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/naim-kishi-395654397/"><strong>Naim Kishi</strong></a>, the superb real-time translator — my first time teaching through live translation. The pauses between sentences turned out to be a blessing, giving me space to read the room and adjust the pace.</li> <li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/abid-satwilkar-17855457/"><strong>Abid Satwilkar</strong></a> from Community Revival, for trusting me with the assignment and supporting the week throughout.</li> <li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/fredewing/"><strong>Fred Ewing</strong></a>, known to just about every modeller in the UK, for the introduction and encouragement.</li> </ul> <p>It was a hugely positive week — and with luck, future training sessions will welcome a more gender-diverse group of participants as opportunities for women in transport continue to grow across Saudi Arabia.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2025-12-05_Pic1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2025-12-05_Pic1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2025-12-05_Pic1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-12-05_Pic1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2025-12-05_Pic2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2025-12-05_Pic2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2025-12-05_Pic2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-12-05_Pic2.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2025-12-05_Pic3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2025-12-05_Pic3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2025-12-05_Pic3-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-12-05_Pic3.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <hr/> <p>If you’re interested in executive training, analytics capability-building, or tailored workshops on transport modelling and data, feel free to <a href="mailto:jeff@amodellis.com"><b>get in touch</b></a>. Amodellis is always keen to collaborate and share knowledge with teams around the world.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="Training"/><category term="SaudiArabia"/><category term="Visualisation"/><category term="AI"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections on delivering a 4-day executive training programme]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Amodellis and the Future of Transport Modelling</title><link href="https://amodellis.github.io/blog/2025/firstpost/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amodellis and the Future of Transport Modelling"/><published>2025-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amodellis.github.io/blog/2025/firstpost</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amodellis.github.io/blog/2025/firstpost/"><![CDATA[<p>For more than twenty years, I have worked at the intersection of transport data, modelling and decision-making. My career began in 2003, straight out of university, building traditional four-stage models — tools that, whilst theoretically imperfect, remain remarkably effective at approximating real-world impacts.</p> <p>One of the projects I am still proud of is the Region of Waterloo LRT work I contributed to in Canada. Years later, seeing the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ion_rapid_transit">ION rapid transit</a> thrive is oddly comforting: a reminder that even the humble four-stage trip-based model, handled with care (and under excellent guidance from mentors like Dave Crowley, Jim Chim and Karoly Krajczar), can stand the test of time.</p> <p>Since 2012, most of my career has been in the UK — home to one of the most sophisticated appraisal frameworks in the world. I have been lucky enough to work on large national models, rail systems, public-transport modelling, bus analytics and more recently, intense investment-grade Traffic &amp; Revenue (T&amp;R) due-diligence work. That last piece was incredibly eye-opening: commercially sensitive, complex, high-stake, high-pressure and requiring absolute diligence. It also reminded me of an important truth — advanced modelling techniques are not always the best tools for managing risk.</p> <p>This year, I finally had a chance to pause and think carefully about the future. And so, <em>Amodellis Ltd.</em> was born — not out of a dramatic reinvention, but out of a desire to step back, reassess where the field is heading, and contribute meaningfully to that direction.</p> <h3 id="three-reckonings-about-the-future-of-transport-modelling"><strong>Three Reckonings About the Future of Transport Modelling</strong></h3> <h3 id="1-ai-will-reshape-modelling-whether-we-like-it-or-not"><strong>1. AI will reshape modelling whether we like it or not.</strong></h3> <p>We are well past the deep learning hype phase and now firmly in the era of agentic AI. Behavioural models remain essential, but it is naïve to think transport modelling can remain unchanged whilst every other analytical discipline transforms.</p> <p>Recently, a thought-provoking post from <a href="https://x.com/sebkrier/status/1994796202760528113">Seb Krier</a> caught my attention, highlighting the rise of <strong>multi-agent systems</strong>. The future will not be “one clever model for everyone”, but ecosystems of specialised agents modelling cooperation, competition, social dynamics, and spatial interactions.</p> <p>This future feels distant — but the time to prepare is now.</p> <h3 id="2-traditional-models-struggle-with-supply-driven-systems"><strong>2. Traditional models struggle with supply-driven systems.</strong></h3> <p>Not too long ago, during a bid, I was asked to forecast demand for a <strong>TNC platform</strong>. We could estimate typical daily trips - but we also knew the real drivers were things our models barely touched:</p> <ul> <li>supply elasticity</li> <li>surge pricing mechanisms</li> <li>queueing and matching systems</li> <li>platform-level optimisation rules</li> </ul> <p>Similarly, key future issues — such as EV charging constraints, autonomous vehicle fleet operations, shared mobility integration, and dynamic pricing mechanisms — sit entirely outside traditional TAG-compliant frameworks.</p> <p>The world is changing faster than our models.</p> <h3 id="3-activity-based-and-agent-based-models-are-coming--ready-or-not"><strong>3. Activity-based and agent-based models are coming — ready or not.</strong></h3> <p>The DfT’s more proactive move toward an <strong>activity-based modelling</strong> (ABM) framework recently is significant and overdue.</p> <p>As a behavioural modeller, I am comfortable with the core ingredients — choice models, segmentation, utility theory. But full ABM/agent-based systems require a larger ecosystem: simulation engines, state machines, temporal dynamics, feedback loops, and <em>ongoing research culture</em> that many consultancies struggle to sustain.</p> <p>There <em>is</em> room for new players — especially those focused on behavioural realism, transparency and modern software practice.</p> <h3 id="so-what-are-we-building"><strong>So what are we building?</strong></h3> <p>Amodellis will be a transport modelling consultancy, yes — but one grounded in research, open tooling and modern workflows. Our vision is incremental and pragmatic:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Build and maintain open-source tools</strong> that support modelling, calibration, analytics and automation.</li> <li><strong>Collaborate on research funding</strong> — with universities, consultancies and government — to prototype next-generation modelling approaches.</li> <li><strong>Help consultancies automate their modelling workflows</strong>, freeing teams to focus on interpretation and decision-making.</li> <li><strong>Deliver high-quality traditional modelling</strong> where it is needed — because appraisal still relies on these systems, and reliability matters.</li> </ol> <p>This is why we have introduced a new service area — <a href="/projects/service_research/">AI-Enabled Transport Research</a> — as part of our long-term strategy. It sits alongside our core services in VDM, PT modelling, T&amp;R forecasting, data analytics and choice modelling.</p> <p>We want to contribute to the future whilst still supporting the present.</p> <h3 id="a-personal-note"><strong>A Personal Note</strong></h3> <p>Founding this company is not about stepping away from modelling — it’s about stepping toward the version of modelling we want to spend the next decade working on.</p> <p>One that is <strong>transparent, open, collaborative, and increasingly intelligent</strong>.</p> <p>If you are an academic, a consultant, a public-sector modeller, a data scientist, or simply someone interested in improving how we understand and forecast human movement — we would love to connect. Let’s explore how we can build the next generation of modelling tools, together.</p> <p>Amodellis begins small, but with purpose.</p> <p>This is day one.</p>]]></content><author><name>Jeff Tjiong</name></author><category term="vision"/><category term="innovation"/><category term="AI"/><category term="transport-futures"/><category term="research"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A personal reflection on why this company now exists, and where we are heading.]]></summary></entry></feed>